Okay, בוקר טוב *Boker tov*.
Today's דף *daf* is לז *Lamed Zayin*. We pick up in the
middle of לו עמוד ב *Lamed Vav Amud Bet*. We're in the
middle of this wonderful סוגיא *sugya* of פרוזבול pruzbul *Pruzbul*. And we
just dealt with the fact about how הלל Hillel, *Hillel* could establish
פרוזבול pruzbul *Pruzbul*. Isn't that undermining a דאורייתא de'oraita, *D'Oraita* principle of
that the שמיטה shemittah *shmitta* nulls the debts? And the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* basically said, well, nowadays the annulling of debts is Rabbinic. And
then it said, okay, well, how did they create that Rabbinic annulling
of debts? That itself is a problem. And then the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* introduced the idea of הפקר בית דין הפקר hefker beis din
hefker, *Hefker Bet Din Hefker*. If they can go ahead and change
issues of ownership of property, which for רש"י Rashi *Rashi* actually was
a sufficient answer even if שמיטה shmita *shmitta* was biblical. That power
gives הלל Hillel. *Hillel* the power to create פרוזבול pruzbul. *Pruzbul* because
they can reassign questions about money. And welcome back. So, but again,
the point תוספות Tosfos? *Tosafot* made is that part of the questions
here is not just the mechanics of פרוזבול pruzbul *Pruzbul* and how
could he use the mechanics to circumvent a דאורייתא de'oraita, *D'Oraita*. The
question was more like how could הלל Hillel's *Hillel* do such a
thing? Like how is it proper to directly attack a דאורייתא Deoraita,
*D'Oraita* or not attack, but like circumvent a דאורייתא de-Oraisa *D'Oraita*? And
that's why it was a more satisfying answer to say it was
Rabbinic. But that actually does point to the way הלל Hillel *Hillel*
framed the issue to begin with. הלל Hillel's *Hillel*, against the popular
conception, did not frame the issue as this is too hard on
the people, let's find a workaround. He framed the issue as there's
a trade-off here for one דאורייתא de-Oraisa *D'Oraita* for the other. You're
annulling the debts, but people are violating the prohibition about not lending
to the poor. So in order to save from a violation of
this מצוה *mitzvah*, we have to find a way to do something
about the annulling of the debts, but it was sort of a
type of a weighing of one דאורייתא de-Oraisa *D'Oraita* against another, and
that's obviously an important way of framing it if you're going to
be circumventing this one דאורייתא *D'Oraita*. Anyway, so that's the basic institution
of פרוזבול pruzbul, *Pruzbul*. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues with the
following. So in the middle of לו עמוד ב *Lamed Vav Amud
Bet*. איבעיא להו Iba'ya lehu. *Iba'u
lehu*. That twelve lines down, line starts with the word מנחילין *manchilin*,
or the next one starts with the word התקין *hitkin*. So about
fifteen lines down, איבעיא להו *Iba'u lehu*. They raised the following question.
כי התקין הלל Hillel's פרוזבול Pruzbul. לדריה הוא דתקין או דלמא לדרי
עלמא נמי תקין *Ki hitkin Hillel Pruzbul l'darei hu d'takkin o dilma
l'darei alma nami takkin*? Did he do it just for his generation
or for future generations? Which is a funny question because he didn't
ask those questions about any of the other תיקון עולם *Tikun Olam*s
that were done in the past.
But maybe, so what is the reason the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* wants
to suggest that this might be limited? So it could be because
it was framed as assessing the reality of his time. ראה הלל
Hillel's שנמנעו העם מלהלוות זה את זה *Ra Hillel she'nimnu ha'am l'halvot
zeh et zeh*. Right, the previous תקנות takkanos *takanot* were not based
on recognizing a current assessment. Okay, I mean, did say by the
אלמנה *almana*, נמנעו מלהשפיע *nimnu m'lehashpiya*, but it was not—but that might
have reflected a more ongoing type of a concern. This sort of
seemed to be like he recognized a particular problem in his time.
So maybe that's partly why. Maybe partly because since it really is
circumventing a דאורייתא *D'Oraita*, it was a very radical thing to do
and maybe we don't want to sort of see this as a
temporary—so, or maybe it was—I mean, as a permanent change. Maybe it
wasn't sort of made as a permanent type of a change. So
we raise the question. Was it for his generation or for future
generations? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, למאי נפקא מינה *L'mai nafka
mina*? What would be a relevant application of this? לבטלוה *Levatlohei*. If
can we annul הלל Hillel's *Hillel*'s תקנה takkanah. *takana*? Okay, so there's
again, like we saw sort of by the case of the אלמנה
*almana*, that there was a pushback in a way of preventing her
from making a נדר *neder* according to some אמוראים Amoraim *Amora'im*, and
here too the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying, well, maybe we don't
like פרוזבול Pruzbul *Pruzbul* anymore. Maybe there's not as much of a
need. Maybe in general we're uncomfortable with it. So maybe we can
annul it. אי אמרת לדריה הוא דתקין *Ei amrat l'darei hu d'takkin*,
if you just did it for his generation, מבטלינן ליה *mevatlinan leh*,
so then we could annul it. Meaning maybe it's enforced now, but
maybe it's more enforced just by habit, but not because it really
has the strength of his ruling behind this. אלא אי אמרת לדרי
עלמא נמי תקין *Ela ei amrat l'darei alma nami takkin*, but if
he established it for all future generations and that was the force
of his תקנה takkanah, *takana*, then we wouldn't have the ability. הא
אין בית דין beis din, יכול לבטל דברי בית דין beis din.
חבירו אלא אם כן גדול gadol? הימנו בחכמה ובמנין *Ha ein beit
din yakhol levatel divrei beit din chavero ela im ken gadol mimenu
be'chochma u've'minyan*. A later בית דין beis din *beit din* cannot annul
the legislation of an earlier one unless it's larger than it. So
are we just doing it now out of like—out of like—מנהג
*minhag* essentially, out of a force of habit or because we want
to be doing it, but not because we actually have the edict
that, you know, about it, or actually is the edict in place?
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. מאי *Mai*? So
what's the story? So תא שמע Ta shma, *Ta shma*. Come in
here. דאמר שמואל Shmuel לא כתבינן פרוזבול Pruzbul אלא אי בבי דינא
דסורא אי בבי דינא דנהרדעא *D'amar Shmuel lo katvinan Pruzbul ela ei
b'veit dina d'Sura ei b'veit dina d'Nahardei*. You can only write a
פרוזבול Pruzbul *Pruzbul* in like these major Torah centers, the בית דין
beis din. *beit din* of סורא *Sura* and the בית דין beis
din *beit din* of נהרדעא *Nahardei*, the central בית דין beis din
*beit din* of the region. Okay. ואי סלקא דעתך לדרי עלמא נמי
תקין *Ve'isalka da'atach l'darei alma nami takkin*. Well, why is that true?
If this was an edict for all generations, דשאר בי דינא bei
dina נמי לכתבו *deshar bei dina nami lichtevu*. Obviously... Hillel wanted this
to be a prevalent type of a tool that people could use,
so why—he should have empowered presumably all בתי דינין. battei dinin. If
they're going to limit it to some central בית דין, beis din
maybe it means that in principle it no longer applies, and you
need—if it's maybe based on the power of הפקר בית דין הפקר,
hefker beis din hefker. right? So maybe you need a central בית
דין. beis din Meaning maybe we're no longer doing it based on
the power of Hillel's original תקנה. takkanah, The power of that original
תקנה, takkanah Hillel's sort of authority, no longer is what makes it
binding. And now if we want it to be binding, we need
the authority of a current בית דין beit din to use the
power of הפקר בית דין הפקר. hefker beis din hefker. Maybe we
need a central בית דין. beit din That would be the only
logic to limit it to these central בתי דינין. battei dinin, Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says and maybe that proves two things. Number
one, that like not only can we annul it, but to some
degree we almost even have to annul it. Maybe the general authority
of this institution no longer is in place, and the only way
that—because Hillel's, you know, authority is no longer behind it, and the
only way to make it work is through a בית דין beit
din. that has really a very—you know, a central בית דין beit
din, that has the power of הפקר בית דין הפקר. hefker beis
din hefker. That's the argument. So the גמרא Gemara says, isn't that—doesn't
that seem to be the case? So the גמרא Gemara says, ואי
סלקא דעתך לדריי עלמא נמי תקין בשאר בתי דינין נמי ליכתבו. ve'isalka
datech ledorei alma nami takkin besha'ar battei dinin nami lichtivu. גמרא Gemara
says no, דילמא כי תקין הלל לדריי עלמא כגון בית דינא דידיה
וכרומן ורב אסי דאלימי לאפוקי ממונא. dilma ki takkin Hillel ledorei alma
kegon beis dina didei u-k'roman ve-Rav Assi de'alimi le'afukei mamona. No, maybe
this is part of Hillel's original תקנה, takkana that even when original
Hillel originally said it, he himself wanted it to be limited to
using a central בית דין Beis Din that is empowered to be
מוציא ממון, motzi mamon, to extract money, that is empowered with הפקר
בית דין הפקר. hefker beis din hefker. Okay, אבל לכולי עלמא לא,
aval lekhuli alma lo, but not for other generations—okay, not for other
בתי דין. battei din. So it is bizarre because if Hillel does
it, he's obviously trying to address a broad societal concern and you
want to make it available, you know, to as many people as
possible. But no, maybe since it's such a radical idea, maybe Hillel
originally limited its use to using a central בית דין Beis Din
that represents the power of הפקר בית דין הפקר. hefker beis din
hefker Okay, so the argument is that if we're limiting it to
these central בתי דינין, battei dinin, maybe they have to do it
on their authority now, not on Hillel's authority, and that's why they
need to be so powerful and central. And the answer is no,
even if it is based on Hillel's authority, maybe Hillel wanted to
limit it to these because it is such this radical thing of
changing the דאורייתא, of circumventing the דאורייתא, he wanted to limit it
to these central בתי דין. battei din.
So we don't know the answer. By the way, parenthetically, this גמרא
Gemara is very important, not only for פרוזבול Pruzbul purposes, but because
it indicates that the idea of הפקר בית דין הפקר hefker beis
din hefker. is limited to central בתי דין battei din and to
the degree that—you know, and highly authoritative בתי דין. battei din. And
to the degree that the idea of אפקעתא דקידושין, hafk'as kiddushin, alright,
is somewhat dependent on הפקר בית דין הפקר. hefker beis din hefker.
רש״י Rashi says because חז״ל Chazal can go ahead and say the
money given, the ring given was really a gift and it wasn't
given as כסף קידושין, kesef kiddushin, so then that's a question of
what type of בתי דין battei din can be involved in the
whole idea of הפקר בית דין הפקר. hefker beis din hefker Okay,
so there's a very important גמרא Gemara in terms of הפקר בית
דין הפקר hefker beis din hefker and how that might intersect with
אפקעתא דקידושין. hafk'as kiddushin. Wait, is that—yeah, that's the legal connection between
הפקר בית דין הפקר hefker beis din hefker. and אפקעתא דקידושין? hafk'as
kiddushin? Not necessarily.
No. Well רש״י Rashi said when the גמרא Gemara said it was
easier to do for כסף, kesef, רש״י Rashi said because of הפקר
בית דין הפקר. hefker beis din hefker, But then the גמרא Gemara
says you do אפקעתא דקידושין hafk'as kiddushin even for like קידושי ביאה.
kiddushei bi'ah. So then the גמרא Gemara says אדעתא דרבנן מקדש. al
da'ata derabbanan mekadesh. That would be fine. That's just because the person's
דעת da'as is to do it based on the will of חז״ל.
Chazal. But at least—but if some—but if at least in the case
of כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin it might partly be based on this
הפקר בית דין Beis Din הפקר, it's just worth noting. But yes,
in the end it seems that אפקעתא דקידושין hafk'as kiddushin is not
based on that. Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. So it's
maybe—it might—according to שמואל Shmuel. it might be limited to central בתי
דין, battei din, but that doesn't totally prove whether it's based on
Hillel's תקנה takanah, or not. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: תא
שמע, Ta shema come and hear, another statement of
שמואל. Shmuel דאמר שמואל האי פרוזבול עולבנא דדייני הוא. De'amar Shmuel hai
pruzbul ulbana de-dayyani hu. This פרוזבול Pruzbul is like the embarrassment, thank
you, of the judges. Okay, so this is consistent with שמואל's Shmuel
other statement that he's trying to very much limit פרוזבול. Pruzbul So
one way he limits it to central בתי דינין, and now he
sort of saying this whole thing is an embarrassment, presumably it's an
embarrassment because we're circumventing this תורה Torah law, what looks like a
תורה Torah law even if שמיטה Shmita nowadays is rabbinic. ואי ישר
חילי חייה אבטליניה. Ve'ei yashar cheili, chaya, avatleinei. If I were to
have the strength, I would nullify it, okay? I'd like to get
rid of this whole institution. So that also might be what provoked
the גמרא's Gemara question of "can we annul it?", because the גמרא
Gemara was aware that שמואל Shmuel had expressed his displeasure with it
and his desire to annul it. Okay. Now again, why is he
trying to annul it? Maybe he feels it's an embarrassment that we're
circumventing this idea, even if it's not a תורה Torah law, it
looks like a תורה Torah law of annulling the debt. Maybe he
felt that in his generation it was counter— productive; maybe he felt
in his generation people would annul their debts and would be prepared
to annul their debts, right? And because we have found this workaround,
or maybe most people wouldn't, and because we found this workaround nobody
is doing it, right? So that's like, you know, that's sort of
like things that happen now by מכירת חמץ, mechirat chametz, right? They
started this whole thing; it became a farce. They started this whole
thing that people had like really had no way of getting rid
of their חמץ chametz and it's thousands of dollars let's say, you
know, whatever, so they went ahead and they created this fiction of
selling their חמץ chametz and, by the way, at the time that
started a lot of פוסקים poskim were against it, okay, but fine,
that got started and there was a real need for it. But
then what happened? Then it became completely widespread, so that ninety-five percent
of people that could just normally get rid of their חמץ chametz
are selling it. And I mean I know somebody who basically if
there's I ממש mamash know this, I told you I am not
making this up. There was a sale a week before פסח Pesach
on like on like cereal, you know, like two dollars a box.
Person bought twenty boxes of it, put it in their basement or
whatever in their pantry and then sold it for פסח, Pesach, you
know. It's like, so the whole thing is like, I would say
ישר חילי, yashar cheili, I would be מבטל mevatel מכירת חמץ mechirat
chametz except for like major, you know, companies that really have like
no choice. So maybe שמואל Shmuel felt in his generation we would
be much better off not to have פרוזבול pruzbul and have people
annul their debts and people are prepared to do that for the
small debts, okay? So, and maybe you know, again, maybe limit it
to big needs and that's why you want to send to have
it in a central בית דין Beis Din for people that really,
you know, have a high threshold, for people that really, really need
to will do it. Okay, so שמואל Shmuel had this position that
he was obviously against it and that's maybe why the גמרא Gemara
raised the question: Is it for future generations based on the authority
of הלל, Hillel or is it possible that we're now just doing
it by habit as it were and that really you could go
ahead and annul it if you wanted to, yes? You said ישר
חילי, yashar cheili, is he talking about physical strength? No, like a
courage or political strength. No,
I don't, well I don't think, I think it more means like
you know if I had the courage based on my colleagues, if
I had the you know religious political strength, if I had the,
you know, I think it sort of means like if I had
the חוצפה chutzpah this is what I would do, okay? That's normally
how it's used. Is it a recognition though that they couldn't muster
a בית דין Beis Din which was גדול? No, it doesn't seem
to be. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says, okay, okay, because,
because the גמרא Gemara, seems to bring, okay, רב נחמן אמר אקימניה.
Rav Nachman amar akimneih. And רב נחמן Rav Nachman says,
sorry, I skipped a line. Okay, אבטליניה. avtalineih. אבטליניה? avtalineih? וכי בית
דין יכול לבטל דברי בית דין חברו אלא אם כן גדול ממנו
בחכמה ובמנין? vechi beit din yachol levatel divrei beit din chavero ela
im kein gadol mimenu bechochma uvevinyan? How did שמואל Shmuel's think he
can do this? You're not allowed to annul, annul unless you're a
larger בית דין. beis din, So
the גמרא Gemara says so it must be that it's no longer
based on the authority of הלל. Hillel That would make sense, and
that's consistent with שמואל's Shmuel other statement. The גמרא Gemara. says no,
הכי קאמר: hachi ka'amar: אם ישר חילי, im yashar cheili, Yosef—and now
you see there they've anticipated your explanation—יותר מהלל אבטליניה. yoter mei-Hillel avtalineih.
It means I know I can't do anything about it because it's
still based on הלל's Hillel authority, but if I only were to
have, it's like it's a wishful statement, if I only were to
be larger than הלל Hillel I would get rid of it. All
right, but nevertheless, you combine the two statements of שמואל Shmuel and
clearly שמואל Shmuel's does not like this institution, he wants to limit
it, it's only a major בית דין, Beis Din create a high
threshold for use, and he ideally would like to get rid of
it. And the גמרא Gemara says that on the face of it
looks like it's not based on הלל's authority anymore, but that might
not be what he's saying; maybe it is based on הלל's authority.
Okay, that's שמואל's Shmuel position. רב נחמן אמר, Rav Nachman amar, one
minute, רב נחמן Rav Nachman says אקימנא. akimnah. No, I would actually
establish it and affirm it. So the גמרא Gemara says אקימנא, akimnah,
you'd establish it, המקיים קיים, hamekayem kayam, who needs you? It's already
established, okay? Again, maybe if it's no longer based on הלל's authority
he would say I would re-establish it, you know, but again that
gets to that question, is it still based on הלל's authority? So
the גמרא Gemara says הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, this is what he's
saying.
אימא בי מלתא, eima bei milta, I would say a thing about
it, דאף על גב דלא כתב ככתב דמי, de'af al gav dela
katav kikatav dami, I would find a way to make it more
widespread, that even if you didn't write a פרוזבול, pruzbul it's as
if it's written. It's so standard that we assume that people want
to write it that you don't even have to say anything. If
you take a look רש"י Rashi says אימא בי מלתא eima bei
milta about twenty lines before the end, אושיב בית דין ואתקין דסתם
מלווין יהיו כמוסרין שטרותיהן לבית דין דאף על גב דלא כתיב יהא
כמי שכתב. oshib beit din ve'atkin destam malvin yihyu kemosrin shetaroteihen lebeit
din de'af al gav dela ketiv yehei kemi shekatav. That it would
just be implicit in every loan, you wouldn't even have to do
anything, it would be automatic. So you have שמואל Shmuel that wants
to basically get rid of it or extremely limit its use, and
you have others that want to make it completely trivial, we're going
to do it automatically, okay? And by the way, in the ראשונים
Rishonim and in the פוסקים poskim there are, I should just say
right now, and this is very relevant because you know רב קוק
Rav Kook discusses this גמרא Gemara as a lens towards the degree
that השמטת כספים hashmatat kesafim reflects on שמטת קרקע, shmitat karka, so
as a lens, you know, and רב קוק Rav Kook had his
workaround about היתר מכירה heter mechira as a lens towards different opinions
about the status of שמיטה Shmita nowadays. And there really are like
three opinions in the ראשונים. Rishonim. Some say it's דאורייתא, okay, even
though there's no יובל yovel which is a hard position but it's
possible, okay, some say that it's דרבנן derabanan which is the
standard. but particularly by שמיטת כספים, Shmitas Kesafim, by some of these
opinions here, and especially if you're talking about שמיטת כספים Shmitas Kesafim
out of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, although the גמרא Gemara says that
when there's שמיטה Shmita in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, there's שמיטת כספים
Shmitas Kesafim דאורייתא out of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, but now if
there's no longer שמיטה Shmita דאורייתא in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, how
much is this does שמיטת כספים Shmitas Kesafim apply outside? So the,
according to some ראשונים Rishonim for some the explain the גמרא, Gemara
to explain how trivial it is for some אמוראים Amoraim in the
גמרא Gemara to just automatically apply פרוזבול. pruzbul, Like you don't even
have to do anything, פרוזבול pruzbul is automatic. Right? So they want
to say that maybe for them the whole idea of annulling debts
nowadays or you know שמיטה Shmita. annulling debts certainly outside of Israel
is only like a מנהג חסידות. Minhag Chasidus. And this actually plays
out according to some פוסקים Poskim and some ראשונים Rishonim and some
פוסקים Poskim you don't really have to do anything, you know? You
don't even have to do a פרוזבול pruzbul like basically they essentially
פסקין pasken like רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, okay, because the whole idea
of annulling the debts even from the outset nowadays is only מנהג
חסידות. Minhag Chasidus. Even if you didn't and you still collect your
loan. Right. Right. So anyway so there so that is the range.
You have שמואל Shmuel that wants to basically completely do away with
פרוזבול pruzbul? or limit it as much as possible, again for what
who knows what the reason is, does he feel the weight of
the idea of שמיטת כספים? Shmitas Kesafim? Is it because the whole
thing is an embarrassment a work-around? Is it because practically it's being
abused and there's really very little need for it? So שמואל Shmuel.
wants to significantly limit פרוזבול pruzbul almost get rid of it. And
רב נחמן Rav Nachman wants to make it automatic and wants to
make it completely prevalent.
Yes. Oh and when you get the chance can you talk about
that תוספות? Tosfos. I think it's a really great תוספות. Tosfos Which?
About you know when something automatically ביטל bittel what kind of בית
דין beis din. do you need? Okay, I don't want to talk
about that now. I mean, I'm sorry, whatever. Okay. Yeah, I'll just
say, I'll mention תוספות Tosfos. has a discussion right when do we
say when when do we say you need a bigger בית דין
beis din. to annul and when do we say that a תקנה
takanah doesn't need a bigger בית דין beit din, is automatically annulled?
Certainly doesn't need a bigger בית דין beit din, if it's not
accepted by the populace that אין לא הציבור יכול לעמוד בה, ein
lo hatzibbur yakhol la'amod bah, if it's not נפשטה בכל
ישראל. nishpashte bekhal Yisrael. There's certain types of תקנות that might not
that might be able to be annulled with a with not a
larger בית דין beis din, or maybe sometimes even automatically. So that's
the issue in תוספות. Tosafos Okay, so you got me to talk
about it. Back to the גמרא. Gemara
So the גמרא Gemara. says like this: איבעיא להו. About again ten
lines from the bottom. They raise the following question: האי עובנא Hai
ubbana this language that's an embarrassment or לישנא דחוצפה הוא? lishana de-chutzpa
hu? Is it well here now the גמרא Gemara says not embarrassment.
Is it like that it's the חוצפה chutzpa of the דיינים? Dayanim?
How did he term חוצפה? chutzpa? Temerity or whatever that they're going
ahead and circumventing a דאורייתא and therefore I want to limit it.
או לישנא דניחוסא הוא? O lishana de-nichusa hu? Or does it mean
it's like it makes their lives too easy? Okay so what does
that mean?
So anyway so רש"י Rashi says רש"י Rashi says that it means
that they only made this, you know, as a way of sort
of making things easier on the judges because if they didn't have
פרוזבול pruzbul. then they would have to everybody would be would be
sort of petitioning the court right before שמיטה shmita, and everybody would
be trying to collect their loans right before שמיטה. shmita So they
made this פרוזבול pruzbul. not so much to help the people but
to alleviate the courts that they don't get flooded with you know
with all... I don't know. Anyway. So that's the גמרא's Gemara question.
It's a strange question. Maybe the גמרא's Gemara pushing back against שמואל.
Shmuel Okay. תא שמע come and hear דאמר עולא de-amar Ulla עלובה
כלה שזינתה בקרב חופתה. Aluva kalla she-zinisa be-kerev chuppasa. So this is
describing the idea of the חטא העגל cheit ha-eigel and it says
it's like a disgrace for the כלה kalla the bride that she
that she fornicated she committed adultery right there under her חופה. chuppah.
There they were receiving the תורה Torah they were standing under the
חופה chuppah at הר סיני Har Sinai right? The whole thing is
a metaphor of the marriage and they go ahead and they worship
other gods and they commit the and they do the עגל. eigel.
So there you see עלובה aluva means that it's a disgrace. Okay.
אמר רב מרי בריה דבת שמואל. Amar Rav Mari bered bat Shmuel.
מאי קרא? Mai k'ra? Now we digress for a moment. What's the
פסוק? pasuk? עד שהמלך במסבו נרדי נתן ריחו. Ad she-hamelekh bi-mesibo nerdi
natan reikho. While the king is still in the חופה chuppah that's
what במסבו bi-mesibo means or like the the meal
my fragrance lost its aroma. So there we are we're right at
the wedding חופה chuppah and I lost my you know my my
charm and my savor my my good repute was all lost because
כלל ישראל K'lal Yisrael went ahead and worshipped the עגל. eigel. אמר
רבא Amar Rava עדיין חביבותא היא גבן. Adayin chavivuso hi gaban. Even
though we have committed this sin we're still beloved to Dad. דכתיב
di-kh'siv נתן natan ולא כתיב הסריח. velo kh'siv hisri'akh.
Because it says my you know fragrance went away but it didn't
say it became it stencht okay so it stank. So therefore it's
not God still loves us. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabbanan. Okay back to
back to this. By the way now that we mentioned עלובה aluva
right like disgraced or whatever we're going to have a little play:
הנעלבין ואינם עולבים, Ha-ne'elavin ve-einam olavin, those that are disgraced but do
not do not return disgrace, שומעין חרפתן ואינם משיבין, shome'in cherpasan ve-einam
meshivin, they hear their disgrace and do not return... He's got the
stuff. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Okay, back to back to this. By
the way, now that we mentioned עלובה, aluvah, right, to be like
disgraced or whatever, we're going to have a little play. הנעלבים ואינם
עולבים, hanelavim ve'einam olovim, those that are disgraced but do not do
not return disgrace. שומעים חרפתם ואינם משיבים, shomim cherpatam ve'einam meshivim, they
hear people, they hear themselves being like shamed and they do not
respond, you know, people embarrassing them and they don't respond. עושים מאהבה
ושמחים בייסורים, osim me'ahava usmechim beyisurin,
serve God out of love and they welcome or they rejoice in
in affliction. It's it's you know it's מכפר עונות mekaper avonos or
something. עליהם הכתוב אומר, alehem hakatuv omer, on them the verse says,
ואוהביו כצאת השמש בגבורתו, ve'ohavav ketzes hashemesh bigvuraso,
and those that love God will be as powerful in the future,
you know, like the like when the sun comes out in its
strength. Okay, so so it's interesting sort of shift from the thinning
of the of the what do you call it of the of
the כלה kallah when the embarrassment or the shame is deserved to
those that are that people shame them unjustly and they're willing to
you know to not to not respond in kind. One wonders I
it might just be like another just a line of אגדתא agadata
like a loose association, but one also wonders if this is a
response to שמואל Shmuel who says that the פרוזבול pruzbul? is the
עולב olev of the דיינים, dayanim, and שמואל Shmuel wants to respond
to being shamed by the פרוזבול pruzbul, and he wants to get
rid of it. So the גמרא Gemara is saying, you know what?
Be the הנעלבים ואינם עולבים. hanelavim ve'einam olovim. Like
you know, deal with that problem that you've got. It's important to
maintain this institution. That's my little דרש drash on the דרש. drash.
Okay, anyway, back to this. But we do see two interesting different
approaches to פרוזבול, pruzbul. to whether we like want to embrace it
and spread it or we want to get rid of it. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this: מאי פרוזבול? mai pruzbul? What does
the word פרוזבול pruzbul, mean? אמר רב חסדא, amar Rav Chisda, פרוז
בולי ובוטי. pruz buli ubuti. Okay, so the פרוז pruz which רש״י
Rashi says means a תקנה, takanah רש״י Rashi says an establishment for
the בולי buli and בוטי. buti. בולי אלו עשירים, buli eilu ashirim,
דכתיב, dechitiv, ושברתי את גאון עוזכם. veshavarti es geon uzechem. ותני רב
יוסף, vetani Rav Yosef, אלו בולאות שביהודה. eilu bulaot shebiYehuda.
These are the בולאות bulaot in יהודה Yehuda
which presumably means the wealthy, the powerful class. בוטי אלו עניים, buti
eilu aniyim, and the בוטי buti are the poor, דכתיב, dechitiv, העבט
תעביטנו, havet avitenu,
you shall surely loan them, like in the word עבוט avot is
like a collateral. So בוטי buti are those that money is lent
to. So he says this is the תקנה takana that helps both
the wealthy and the poor. It helps the poor because people will
lend them money, and it helps the wealthy because it allows them
to collect the money. Now the actual etymology of the word פרוזבול
pruzbul? is close to that, but not exactly that. Basically the word
בולי bulei is a Greek word which is a council.
And I think that here I just I see
well, here, here's from Klein's dictionary. He writes, quote, probably shortened from
Pros Boule Bouliteon, before the assembly of the counselors. So בולי bulei
were the Roman counselors which were the wealthy class or the sort
of, you know, the powerful class, so the גמרא Gemara, is identifying
of בולי buli with עשירים, ashirim, but it's not the עשירים ashirim
who are lending the money. It's the idea that it's essentially you
present it before the court. It's handed over to the court, okay,
from pros, towards, against, before, in the presence of, of בולי, boule,
council, the assembly. Okay, the בולי bulei mentioned here is the same
as the as in the גמרא Gemara although the etymology is different.
The lower house of the modern Greek legislators is known as the
בולי. boule. Okay,
so that's probably that's generally what the understanding is. Something like אג״ב
agav taken up by the court? Or like it's sort of like
לפני הדיינים, lifnei hadayanim, right, you give it you transfer your debt
to the court. Okay, back to the גמרא. Gemara אמר ליה רבא
ללעוזא, amar lei Rava l'lo'aza, רבא Rava said to a foreign speaker,
so maybe they realized that this was of Greek extraction or something.
מאי פרוזבול? mai pruzbul? What's the etymology of the word פרוזבול? pruzbul
אמר ליה, amar lei, פורסא דמילתא, porsa demilsa, which is like the
half of something,
okay, so רש״י Rashi says,
פרוז, pruz, oh no, I'm sorry, it's תקנה takana רש״י Rashi says.
It means something that was done to fix the matter.
Okay, פורסא דמילתא. porsa demilsa. Okay, I don't know how רש״י Rashi
knows פורסא porsa means to fix it. Anyway, back to the גמרא
Gemara or to the
גמרא Gemara continuing. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, amar Rav Yehuda amar
Shmuel, יתומים אינם צריכים פרוזבול, yasomim einam tzerichin pruzbul, orphans who are
coming to collect their father's debt do not need a פרוזבול pruzbul
written for them. Okay, again, maybe we're you know orphans don't have
to be like a ten year old at fathered you know could
be somebody that's forty that's father's died and now has to collect
the debt, but even if you're not sort of, you know, under
age, maybe you're not totally or you know always immediately aware of
the father died like a week before שמיטה, shemitta the you know
the end of the of the שמיטה shemitta year and the the
debts were about to be annulled, it didn't occur to you that
you had to go ahead and take care of all of the
you know of the debts, you weren't even aware of the debts
so you were going to write a פרוזבול. pruzbul She says, well
the father passed to him. What? Passed to the father. I understand,
he was sick for the last year leading up to whatever his
death, I don't under this isn't a good Anyway, the point is
is that we have a little bit of רחמנות rachmanus here, like
you know, that you'll caught in this situation and therefore don't worry
about it. You don't need to write a פרוזבול. pruzbul. We got
it taken care of. Okay, and we'll see why in a minute.
וכן תני רמי בר חמא, vechen tani Rami bar Chama, יתומים אינם
צריכים פרוזבול, yasomim einam tzerichin pruzbul, they don't need to. Now why
not? Maybe because of this whole thing like we saw before about
רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, you know, we can just create this whole
fiction altogether, you know. So maybe you don't even need anything written.
Although רב נחמן Rav Nachman said that maybe as soon as the
debt was written, it was implicitly given over. Here we're not saying
it by everybody, we're just saying it by יתומים. yesomim. So what's
the mechanism through which we sort of say they don't have to
take care of פרוזבול? pruzbul So here's the answer. רבן גמליאל ובית
דינו אביהם של יתומים. Rabban Gamliel u’veis dino avihem shel yesomim. That
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and his בית דין, they are the fathers
of the orphans. They're taking over the concerns of the orphans. Now
why it mentions רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel is not clear, רש"י Rashi
says that that's just when this משנה mishna was written, but it
basically means that we as חז"ל Chazal sort of take
our responsibility to protect their interests. So since we see it as
our responsibility to protect their interests, that's not just what motivated us
to say you don't have to write a פרוזבול, pruzbul that's the
mechanism why you don't have to write a פרוזבול. pruzbul... Since we're
protecting your interests, your loans are already under our care. So since
the money owed to you, we're presenting ourselves as the court is
here to protect the interests of the orphans, so their loans are
already our responsibility. Okay, not the money they borrowed, the money owed
to them is already our responsibility and they don't have to give
the loans over to the court. So that's why they don't need
to do it. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says תנן התם.
tnan hatam. So now we're going to continue to see these issues.
On the one hand, what type of requirements do we make that
might sort of be technical as a way of making it seem
like we're doing something real here in terms of the פרוזבול, pruzbul,
and on the other hand, to what degree do we try to
make it very, very easy for people to do the פרוזבול? pruzbul
Some of that tension that existed between שמואל and רב נחמן Rav
Nachman earlier. So, yes? רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama is an
אמורא? Amora?
Yeah. So it's interesting that רש"י Rashi says that he's bringing a
ברייתא braisa or
that אמוראים Amoraim bring ברייתות braisos all the time? Yeah. So no,
תני, tani, he brings the ברייתא, braisa, right. Isn't that interesting? Yeah,
I mean that happens all the time.
Okay, תנן התם. tnan hatam. We taught over there in שביעית, Shevi'is,
אין כותבין פרוזבול אלא על הקרקע. ein kosvin pruzbul ella al hakaraka.
You can only write a פרוזבול Proszbul, if the debtor has land.
Now why is this? Okay, so there could be two reasons. רש"י
Rashi and תוספות Tosafos, both say one but they also imply the
other. One reason רש"י just says is well, we only allowed a
תקנה takkanah. of פרוזבול Proszbul. for classic cases, standard cases. We don't
make cases that are לא שכיח. lo shechiach. And a classic case
of lending money is that somebody has land. You only lend money
to somebody with land so you can collect from it. Now the
reality is that that's really not true on small loans. Also there's
things such as collateral that people give when they don't have land,
but maybe that's part of the point. Maybe part of the point
is like I said before, we only want this פרוזבול Proszbul to
address cases of large loans. Maybe small loans, people will be okay
with the fact that שמיטה Shmita will annul. So maybe we wanted
to limit it to cases where you were lending with land present,
because not only is that like a common case, but that also
like limits it to cases which need the תקנה of פרוזבול. Proszbul.
The other explanation, one second, is as we're going to see later,
there's two types of loans—I mean, there's more, but there's two types
that are always quoted together—that שמיטה Shmita does not annul. A loan
that's given over to the court to collect because then it's not
לא יגוש, lo yigosh, I am not personally collecting it, okay, and
a loan that actually is
of, what do you call it, when I have a collateral for
the loan. Why is that not, the court doesn't annul? I mean,
I'm anticipating the גמרא Gemara later but you'll see why I'm introducing
it now, is because if I'm holding onto collateral I don't have
to exact the money from you. I don't have to go to
you and pressure you and so on, I'm just already in possession
of the loan, as it were. So there's less of a collecting
that needs to be done. So to some degree the פרוזבול Proszbul.
works by מוסר שטרותיו לבית דין. moseir shetarosav l'veis din. It sort
of is like giving it over, even though it's somewhat of a
fiction, that's giving it over to the court. But what also the
קרקע karaka does is it allows you to address it from the
other end. If there is real estate that can be collected, if
you've got money in a bank and I have to find your
assets or whatever, it's much more out of my reach. But if
there's real estate, it's much more in my reach. You can't hide
the real estate, right? The court can always go and seize it.
So to some degree, maybe it's more like it's been somewhat collected
already and that's an idea we're going to see. So the combination
of פרוזבול Proszbul. with קרקע karaka might just be because it limits
it to the types of loans, classic loans, not tiny loans, but
also because it might help with some mechanics. It might make it
more like the loan is already like more easily collected and therefore
less, more already in my hand. Yes, David, you had a question.
Weren't we focusing on the idea that the people who had no
money weren't lending to the poor? Right. So how did poor have
land? We're about to see that in a minute. Hold on. Yes,
I'm sorry for this, just let's review, so the poor could have
a little plot of land that you, right. Well, I don't know
the reality, though. I mean, there're a lot of poor farmers out
there, I'm serious, like in an agricultural society, like it could be
everybody had land but you had the people that had the big
estate and the people that were barely making a
living, but might be that like, but yeah, so I don't know
enough the reality. פרוזדור prozdor is, פרוזבול... Proszbul פרוזדור prozdor is something
else, פרוזבול, Proszbul sorry, the פרוזבול Proszbul. is מוסר שטרותיו לבית דין.
moseir shetarosav l'veis din. To who actually collects the money to, like
where's the money actually come from to repay the debtor? The debtor.
I mean eventually he's going to pay it back, like anyway would
eventually pay it back. בית דין doesn't collect. After שמיטה Shmita. is
over and whatever they say give me back my authority to collect
my loan. He just holds onto it long enough for שמיטה shemittah
not to annul it.
Right. I mean nothing there's no official
regiving, they hold onto it for it's all a fiction. It's all
a fiction. They're holding onto it long enough to protect it from
the annulling of annulment of שמיטה. shemittah Okay fine. Now the גמרא
Gemara deals with this issue about what happens if the debtor doesn't
have land. Okay so let's take a look. אם אין לו, im
ein lo, if the debtor doesn't have land, see that, מזכהו בתוך
שדהו, mezakehu besoch sodehu, so you'll do the guy a favor, I
will now give you a square inch of my land, me the
creditor give you the debtor a square inch of my land, so
that will now allow me to write a פרוזבול, pruzbul okay, so
and you can do that? Well you yeah I mean I can
do it through a third party though. You don't have to agree.
כל שהוא, kol shehu, even a tiny amount. But wouldn't that be
a חוב chov for you then? Yeah that's an interesting point. איך
זכין לאדם שלא בפניו. ech zachin leadam shelo befonav. So the idea
since the actual taking possession of קרקע karka is a זכות, zechus,
even though I'm going to use it to hurt your interest, somehow
we can still do it. Okay but this whole thing is a
fiction. But it's a good point. It's a זכין zachin that ultimately
hurts you. Okay anyway
כל שהוא, kol shehu, even a small amount. וכמה כל שהוא, vechama
kol shehu, how much is a small amount? אמר רב חייא בר
אשי, amar Rav Chiya bar Ashi, gotta love the גמרא, Gemara אמר
רב, amar Rav, אפילו קלח של כרוב, afilu klach shel kruv, even
if it's like just one like head of cabbage, even that a
square inch that would be enough. All right.
The size of a cabbage head. All right. אמר רב יהודה, amar
Rav Yehuda, אפילו השאילו מקום לתנור וכירים, afilu hishilo makom letanur vechira-im,
even if he doesn't own the plot of land, even if he
just has it lent to
him, I've lent you space to use your oven on my property.
So since you have right to a certain space area of my
property, that's like you have land and that allows me to write
a פרוזבול. pruzbul, Okay. לתנור וכירים. letanur vechira-im. כותבין עליו פרוזבול. kotvin
alav Proszbul. איני והא תני הלל, eini veha tani Hillel, isn't that
really true? But didn't הלל teach אין כותבין פרוזבול אלא אעציץ נקוב.
ein kotvin Proszbul ela a-atzis nakuv. הלל himself taught that you can
only write a פרוזבול pruzbul. if the guy has the famous flower
pot with the hole in it. בלבד. bilvad. So נקוב אין שאינו
נקוב לא. nakuv ein she-eino nakuv lo. So if the debtor had
a flower pot without a hole in it I couldn't write a
פרוזבול. pruzbul. But the גמרא Gemara says ואמאי, ve'amai, why? Because then
it wouldn't be considered קרקע. karka. But why not? והאיכא
מקומו. veha'ika mekomo. But where's he putting his flower pot? You need
a place to hang your hat, you need a place to put
your flower pot. So where are you putting your flower pot? Presumably
either on your own land or on space some land that somebody
lent you, somebody allowed you to put your flower pot on their
land. So then you have rights to that pot of land that
your flower pot is on. So if borrowed land
works why should anything other than the shirt on your back, if
you have any place to put any possession,
you
should be able to write a
פרוזבול. pruzbul Okay. So the גמרא Gemara, says, and I don't understand
the answer, the גמרא Gemara says לא צריכא דמנח אסיכי. lo tzricha
demanach asichi.
It's not directly on the ground, it's on like pegs. Okay but
I don't get it, who gives you right to put the pegs
on the ground? So
maybe it's like I let you put your flower pot on my
table. Don't put it on the floor, you can put it on
the table. So maybe you don't have rights to actually the ground
itself. I lent you space on my table but I didn't lend
you space on the property itself. Thank you so much. Are we
sure that that's being discussed or is it that the עציץ הנקוב
atzis hanakuv itself is the property? No that's the point. The גמרא
Gemara says even if the עציץ atzis is לא נקוב lo nakuv
and it's not itself the property, if property can include the right
to use land, so any place that you're putting your possession is
land. גמרא Gemara says no maybe you only have right to put
your possessions on somebody's table. You don't have rights to put your
possessions on somebody's ground. And therefore you have no rights to anybody's
land and therefore you can't write a פרוזבול. pruzbul, That would be
the what? Yeah apparently that's not enough.
Okay anyway but once obviously what the גמרא Gemara is doing here
is it's trying to have this requirement maybe to satisfy the mechanism
of פרוזבול pruzbul maybe as I said to make פרוזבול pruzbul, a
little more limited to not make it that everybody does it, right
sort of like Shmuel's push. And then we have the push back
and says okay you need קרקע karka let me tell you something
everybody's got קרקע. karka. Even if you have a right to just
put your possessions down on a square inch of land you've got
קרקע. karka. So you can always write a פרוזבול. pruzbul. Okay unless
this crazy case that all you can do is keep your stuff
on somebody's table but you can't actually put it on the floor.
All right so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, רב אשי
מקני ליה גידמא דדיקלא, Rav Ashi makni leh gidma dedikla, רב
אשי Rav Ashi transferred the... Like a you know what do you
call
it a נו nu a like a trunk
of a palm tree, thank you, a trunk of a palm tree
he transferred it to somebody, the person that he that owed him
money through a third party he transferred the trunk and he wrote
a פרוזבול pruzbul. on it.
רבנן דבי רב אשי, Rabbanan d'bei Rav Ashi, the
rabbis of
רב אשי's Rav Ashi ישיבה, yeshiva, משו מילי להדדי. mashi milai l'hadadi.
They didn't write anything. They just verbally gave over their loans. They
said oh you know there they were in ישיבה, yeshiva, they went
over to the next table, they said hey you three guys, stop
learning for a second. You're my בית דין. I'm giving you over
my loans. Fine, goodbye. Hey wait, now I'm giving you over my
loans. Okay fine goodbye, we're done. Okay so that's what they did.
Okay so that's sort of like what רב נחמן Rav Nachman said,
I want to make it almost automatic. And based on this some
ראשונים rishonim say that this is because like maybe שמיטת כספים shemittas
kesafim nowadays is maybe only מידת חסידות midas chasidus and therefore you
know at least some of these אמוראים maybe felt that and therefore
they felt you just trivial, anything you do as a זכר zecher
to acknowledge that it exists suffices. Okay but some want to say
well maybe it's only תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, we don't we don't
trust them to abuse this or whatever, they'll know they'll you know
they'll understand that and so on. So it's interesting how some of
this plays out להלכה. l'halacha. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this: משו מילי להדדי. mashi milai l'hadadi. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
משו מילי לרבי חייא בר אבא. mashi milai l'Rabbi Chiya bar Abba.
So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said he gave it over verbally to
רבי חייא בר אבא, Rabbi Chiya bar Abba, you and your two
friends there you'll be my
בית דין.
אמר ליה, amar lei, he said to
him, לא צריכינא מידי אחריני, lo tzrichina midi achrini, do I not
he says do I need to do anything else? אמר ליה, amar
lei, לא צריכת, lo tzrichas, no you don't, goodbye. Okay. Maybe that's
like a יחיד מומחה yachid mumche can also be? Maybe. That's that's
an interesting question, I don't know, I don't know. Anyway, תנו רבנן:
tanu rabbanan: אין לו קרקע ולארב יש לו קרקע. ein lo karka
v'la'arev yesh lo karka. If he has no land, okay, but the
creditor this is basic it seems clearly there was a development, right?
It seems clearly that originally when they said you needed land it
was a serious thing and now we've made it very much of
a fiction, the idea of land. To the point that here not
only does it seem like they didn't worry if the guy had
land, they didn't even worry to write a פרוזבול, pruzbul, they just
did it all verbally and they were done, just said a few
words, magic, it was done. Okay but now we're going back and
quoting the earlier משניות mishnayos that seem to have been in a
time when it was a more serious type of a thing and
you really did need land. And then it's going to deal with
well what happens if the debtor didn't have land? Okay. אין לו
קרקע, ein lo karka, the debtor didn't have land, ולארב יש לו
קרקע, v'la'arev yesh lo karka, but the guarantor of the loan had
land. כותבין עליו פרוזבול, kotvin alav pruzbul, that would be okay because
eventually ultimately you could collect the land from the guarantor.
Okay. לא ולארב אין לו קרקע, lo v'la'arev ein lo karka, if
the debtor and the guarantor did not have land, ולחייב לו יש
לו קרקע, u'lechayav lo yesh lo karka, but so I lent money
to ראובן. Reuven. ראובן Reuven doesn't have land, שמעון Shimon the creditor
guarantor doesn't have land. But לוי Levi owes money to ראובן Reuven
and לוי Levi has land. So in that case כותבין עליו פרוזבול,
kotvin alav pruzbul, that I could also write a פרוזבול. pruzbul, Why?
Because ultimately I could get access to לוי's Levi land. How could
I get access to לוי's Levi land? מדרב נתן, mi'd'Rav Natan, from
what רב נתן Rav Natan says. דתניא רב נתן: d'tanya Rav Natan:
מנין לנושה בחברו מנה, minalan l'noshe bechavero maneh, how do I know
that if I have lent somebody a hundred dollars, וחברו בחברו מנה,
v'chavero bechavero maneh,
and he has lent somebody else a hundred dollars, שמוציאין מזה ונותנין
לזה, shemotzi'in mizeh v'nosnin lizeh,
that I could get from I could sort of you know jump
over the middle guy. I can take so לוי Levi owes ראובן
Reuven money, ראובן Reuven owes me money, I can go straight to
לוי Levi and collect the money, okay? And therefore I have access
to that land and therefore I can write פרוזבול. Prozbul. How do
you know you can do that? תלמוד לומר ונתן לאשר אשם לו,
talmud lomar v'nasan la'asher asham lo, you give to the person to
whom the you know the that the guilt is you know or
the debt is due I mean here it's being read as debt
the debt is owed, so eventually that money is coming to me,
I can go straight to that guy. Okay. תנן התם, tnan hatam,
we taught over there, השביעית משמטת את המלוה בין בשטר בין שלא
בשטר. ha'shevi'is meshametes es hamalveh bein beshtar bein shelo beshtar.
This is all משניות mishnayos from שביעית. shevi'is. So okay. השביעית משמטת
את המלוה, ha'shevi'is meshametes es hamalveh,
שמיטה shemittah annuls the loans. By the way, what we haven't said
yet is as people but as people know because we just finished
a שמיטה shemittah, year is that it annuls the loans at the
end, okay, not at the beginning of the year, at the end
of the year. Although there's a רמב"ם Rambam in פירוש המשניות Peirush
HaMishnayos that seems to have vacillated about that. But anyway it's basically
it annuls the loans at the end. Okay. השביעית משמטת את המלוה
בין בשטר בין שלא בשטר. ha'shevi'is meshametes es hamalveh bein beshtar bein
shelo beshtar. That's why you did the פרוזבול Prozbul. right before ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah of the year after of you know right at
the end of the שמיטה shmita year. Okay. Whether it annuls loans
whether you before פרוזבול, Prozbul, in terms of the mechanism of שמיטה,
shmita whether the loan was with a שטר, shtar, with a document.
Whether or not. In other words, the purpose of a document is
that usually a document means not only that it'll be easier proven
and easier to collect, but also that there would be liens on
קרקע. karka. Okay, and that as we've seen, קרקע karka is a
relevant factor. Well, we'll take a look. But this was before פרוזבול
Prozbul anyway. This was, you know, without the context of פרוזבול, Prozbul
just סתם דריש משנה בשמאי. stam de-reish mishna be-shammai. Okay, בין בשמאי
ובין בהלל. bein be-shammai u-vein be-hillel. רב ושמואל דאמרי תרוייהו. Rav u-Shmuel
de-amri tarvaihu. Now what does a שטר shtar mean that it annuls?
בשטר be-shtar means שטר שיש בו אחריות נכסים. shtar she-yesh bo achrayut
nechasim. If the שטר shtar actually has written in it that there
are liens on the land. שלא בשטר, shelo be-shtar, שאין בו אחריות
נכסים. she-ein bo achrayut nechasim.
Without a שטר shtar doesn't literally mean without a שטר. shtar. It
means even a שטר shtar that doesn't have it literally written in.
And therefore it basically annuls all debts, even a שטר shtar that
has explicitly written liens into it and כל שכן מלווה על פה.
kol she-ken milveh al peh. And therefore it certainly annuls even a
more abstract
debt like... these debts are more concrete. A more abstract debt like
a purely verbal debt. That's how they explain it. רבי יוחנן ורבי
שמעון בן לקיש דאמרי תרוייהו. Rabbi Yochanan ve-Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish de-amri
tarvaihu. רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש Rabbi Yochanan ve-Resh Lakish say no. בשטר,
be-shtar, when it says that it annuls a debt that has a
document, that's שטר שאין בו אחריות נכסים. shtar she-ein bo achrayut nechasim.
That's a document that does not have the actual liens explicitly written
into it. Okay,
and שלא בשטר shelo be-shtar without a שטר shtar is what it
sounds like, מלווה על פה. milveh al peh. It's a verbal debt.
There's no document at all. So what's the point of saying that?
Because they want to say there's one type of שטר shtar that
is so powerful that שמיטה shmita is not משמט meshamet even without
a פרוזבול. Prozbul אבל שטר שיש בו אחריות נכסים אינו משמט. aval
shtar she-yesh bo achrayut nechasim eino meshamet.
If it has the actual liens written in, then it is not
משמט. meshamet. Now, why not? So one of the reasons could be,
and why does it matter that it's written in? Don't we say
that every שטר shtar has liens even if you don't explicitly label
it? So here's a classic לומדות lomdus that they say in the
ישיבה, yeshiva, which is that even if there's always liens for a
debt in a שטר, shtar, even if it's not explicitly written, there's
a concept of how do you conceptualize the idea of a lien.
Do you conceptualize the idea of a lien as a right that
I can exercise or do you conceptualize the idea of a lien
as an actual partial ownership of the property itself? Okay, and that
then I can be sort of made fully, you know, manifest when
I actually am collecting the debt, but it's actually already an ownership
in the property. So some ראשונים Rishonim that imply this that when
a שטר shtar is written...
when the אחריות achrayut are written in the שטר, shtar, the שטר
shtar itself serves, get ready for this, as also a שטר מכר,
shtar mecher, a שטר shtar that transfers rights of your property to
me. So you bent $1,000 to me and we identified and we
said I have rights now, I have liens on your property. That
שטר shtar is not only a שטר ראיה shtar re'ayah to prove
that you owe me money, it's a שטר shtar to transfer those
property rights to me. You can't go on the property before the
debt's due? No. Those rights allow me to seize it when the
debt isn't paid. If you don't pay. Right, when the debt isn't
paid. But they are actual rights in the property itself. It's actually
a partial ownership, not conditional, a sort of type of an ownership
of the property. Okay. So anyway if you understand it that way,
you understand why שמיטה shmita wouldn't be משמט meshamet because it's now
actually more in my possession already. Right, it's less of a debt.
It's already in something that I already partially own. Okay. So that's
the position of ריש לקיש Resh Lakish and רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
תניא
כוותיה דרבי יוחנן ורבי שמעון בן לקיש. tanya ke-vatei de-rabbi yochanan ve-rabbi
shimon ben lakish. And we taught a ברייתא braita like them. שטר
חוב משמט. shtar chov meshamet. A שטר, shtar,
if the debt's in a document, it is annulled. ואם יש בו
אחריות נכסים אינו משמט. ve-im yesh bo achrayut nechasim eino meshamet. But
if it's written in it is liens, it is not. And this
is without פרוזבול. This is just on its own. Okay. תניא אידך.
tanya idach. We taught another ברייתא. braita. שיחד לו שדה אחת בהלוואתו
אינו משמט. si-ched lo sadeh achat be-halva'ato eino meshamet. If you specifically
identified the field that you plan on collecting from, on taking if
the debt isn't paid, then it's not משמט. meshamet. Then it's again
like that field's already in your possession. ולא עוד אלא אפילו כתב
כל נכסיי אחראין וערבאין לך אינו משמט. ve-lo od ela afilu katav
kol nechasai achra'in ve-arva'in lach eino meshamet. Even if you didn't identify
the particular field. You just said all of my property is encumbered,
all of my property... you have a lien on all my property.
Meaning you wrote the אחריות achrayut in the שטר, shtar, then it's
not משמט. meshamet. So that's again like ריש לקיש Resh Lakish and
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, that when the אחריות achrayut is written in
the שטר, shtar, it's like you already have some possession in the
property and you don't need a פרוזבול, even without any
פרוזבול, even מעיקר הדין, me-ikar ha-din, the שמיטה Shmita? is not משמט
meshamet that. Yes. Why is the term נכסים nechasim used to designate
קרקע karka as opposed to מטלטלין? metaltelin? It's נכסים שיש להם אחריות.
nechasim she-yesh lahem achrayut. That was the more... that was the more
actually the more older way of referring to קרקע. karka. Yes. This
means all my property... meaning all property? Well, or only landed property.
The property that can have a lien is the landed property. קריביה
דרב אסי הוה ליה ההוא שטרא. kerivei de-rav assi hava lei hahu
shtra. So רב אסי's Rav Assi relative had a שטר, shtar, דהוה
כתיב ביה אחריות נכסים. di-hava ketiv bei achrayut nechasim. And money was
owed to him, and the שטר shtar had written in it explicitly
the liens. אתא לקמיה דרב אסי אמר ליה משמט או אינו משמט.
ata lakamei de-rav assi amar lei meshamet o eino meshamet. He came
to רב אסי Rav Assi and he said to him, is
שמיטה Shmita going to... I don't
know, maybe he didn't like the answer. But the point was he
loved the answer, but he's gonna have to collect. It's not enough
to have one person's opinion. You have to know that you're going
to be able to win the case. So he wanted to make
sure that there was a rabbinic consensus about this, right? You understand,
it's not like I'm saying, "Am I allowed to do this on
Shabbos?" I get the answer I want, I'm not going to ask
somebody else. Okay, but here you want to know, "Am I going
to be able to collect this debt after שמיטה?" Shmita So you
don't just want one person's opinion. You want to make sure that
there's a rabbinic consensus about this, or else I'm going to have
to write a פרוזבול. Which was relative? Well, that's true also. All
right, maybe that's true also. He came to Rabbi Yochanan. אמר ליה:
Amar leh: "משמט". Meshamet So Rabbi Yochanan said, "No, I'm sorry, שמיטה's
Shmita going to annul it. You better write a פרוזבול." Okay, so
שבקיה ואזל קמיה דרבי יוחנן. Shavkei v-azal kamei d-Rabbi Yochanan. אמר ליה:
Amar leh:
"משמט". Meshamet So אזל azal Rav Assi, so Rav Assi, who said
it's not going to be משמט, meshamet, and he heard back that
Rabbi Yochanan said that it would. So now he went קמיה דרבי
יוחנן. kamei d-Rabbi Yochanan. He said to Rabbi Yochanan, "אמר ליה משמט
או אינו משמט?" amar leh meshamet o einu meshamet? He said, "Wait,
wait, what did you say? I want to make sure, what do
you think about this loan? Is it going to be annulled or
not?" אמר ליה: Amar leh: "משמט". Meshamet It's going to be annulled.
"והא מר הוא אמר אינו משמט?" Ve-ha mar hu amar einu meshamet?
But we just learned 10 lines earlier in the גמרא—he Gemara didn't
say that anyway—you just said, you and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said,
that if a שטרא shtar has אחריות נכסים achrayut nechasim written into
it, it's not annulled. What are you פוסק-ing paskin otherwise?
אמר ליה: Amar leh: "וכי מפני שאנו מדמים נעשה מעשה?" Ve-chi mipnei
she-anu medamim naaseh maaseh? What, just because we can make an argument
means we should rule by it? Of course, like what's all of
ש"ס Shas if not that? So you might remember that Rabbi Yochanan
had that line earlier in the גמרא, Gemara but there he had
it when he was comparing two unlike cases. There was a real
מדמים. medamim. He was comparing the discussion about writing by Shabbos to
writing by a גט. get. So there you could say that's just
an analogy, maybe there's completely different הלכות halachos should govern. Okay, but
here, it's not an analogy, it's not מדמים. medamim. He's actually arguing.
There's a question that if it's like, you know, what are the
parameters of what types of debts are שמיטה shmita משמט, meshamet, and,
you know, but here it just means like look, like maybe he
felt like I didn't have any textual evidence, which is true by
the way. The earlier argument had no textual evidence. So since just
because we think something intuitively is correct, that this should be different
and שמיטה should not be משמט, meshamet, right, I don't have any
textual evidence, and I'm not prepared to rule by it. Okay, so
that was a very interesting reversal. Earlier context, earlier discussion was just
like they were sort of banding about ideas in the בית מדרש?
beit midrash? Well, apparently, but now the גמרא's Gemara going to say,
"What do you mean? They did have textual evidence." Meaning you didn't
have a פסוק, pasuk, but you had ברייתות braitas that ruled like
it. At least you had a ברייתא braita that supported you. It
wasn't just סתם סברא. stam svara. Okay, the גמרא Gemara says: "והא".
Ve-ha So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: "אמר ליה והא תניא כוותיה דמר?" Amar leh ve-ha tanya kevasei
d-mar? But we got a ברייתא! braita! So, okay, you know, I
understand initially maybe you said it as a סברא, svara, like it
seems to me that this is enough of an ownership of the
land as not משמט. meshamet. But we had a ברייתא braita that
supported you. Okay. אמר ליה: Amar leh: "דילמא היא בית שמאי היא?"
Dilma hi beit Shammai hi? I'm not sure that ברייתא braita is
exactly, you know, can I use it to back up my opinion?
Because maybe it follows an opinion of בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. What's
בית שמאי? Beit Shammai? "דאמר שטר העומד לגבות כגבוי דמי". d-amar shtar
ha-omed ligvos k-gavuy dami We know בית שמאי Beit Shammai says elsewhere
that if you have a document or a debt in a document
and the time has come for the debt to be paid, it's
like it's already in your possession. It's like the money is already
in your possession. So just because there are opinions out there that
certain types of debts with שטרות shtaros are not משמט, meshamet, I
don't know if we can rely on them for how we, you
know, because we understand that until the debt's been paid it's not
in your possession like בית הלל. Beit Hillel. Okay, so it's quite
interesting. It was a good, very good סברא svara supporting ברייתות, braitas,
but when push comes to shove he's not willing to do it.
Maybe because it was so easy to write a פרוזבול, you know,
why not just go ahead and write a פרוזבול and take care
of it that way? All right, so now the גמרא continues:
"תנן התם". Tenan hatam We taught over there... back to משנה Mishna
in שביעית. Shevi'it. We're just going through the משניות. Mishnayot. The tenth
perek of שביעית, Shevi'it, most of שביעית Shevi'it is about שמיטת קרקע.
Shmitat Karka. The tenth perek is all devoted to שמיטת כספים. Shmitat
Kesafim. And this גמרא is basically doing a quick survey of the
משניות Mishnayot of the tenth perek of שביעית. Shevi'it. Okay, so, תנן
התם. Tenan hatam. We taught over there, because there's no בבלי Bavli
on שביעית. Shevi'it. Okay,
המלווה את חברו חוב על המשכון. ha-malveh et chavero chov al ha-mashkon.
If you lend money and you actually have taken collateral, okay, so
you don't have קרקע karka but you've got collateral. והמוסר שטרותיו לבית
דין. Ve-ha-moseir shtarotav le-veit din. Or if you actually, really give over
the שטרא shtar to בית דין, אין משמטין. ein mameshamtin. That's without
פרוזבול's הלל's תקנה. That's like מעיקר הדין. me-ikar ha-din. A real giving
over of the שטרא shtar to בית דין, it's not משמט, meshamet,
and a real collateral. And as we said,
הלל's פרוזבול could be like a fiction of מוסר שטרותיו לבית דין.
moseir shtarotav le-veit din. It works with that idea. It's not the
real thing, but that's at least the fiction, it works as if
it's that. Okay, but here we have in addition to that the
idea of משכון, mashkon, which is similar to things we've been talking
about when the thing is in your possession. Okay, so the גמרא
says like this: "אין משמטין". Ein mameshamtin "בשלמא מוסר שטרותיו לבית דין",
Bishlama moseir shtarotav le-veit din I get. When you hand it over
to a בית דין, בשלמא bishlama דתפסי להו
בי דינא, d'tafsi lehu bei dina, בי דינא is the one that's
in possession of it and they have the power to collect it,
so maybe it's like they've already collected it, or certainly it's not
that you are no longer in the process of collecting and therefore
it's not annulled. אלא מה למשכון מאי טעמא? ella mah l'mashkon mai
ta'ama? But why if you've got collateral? Okay, so it seems like
the answer's obvious given what we've been alluding to by קרקע, karka,
but let's see what the גמרא says. אמר רבא amar Rava משום
דתפסי ליה mishum d'tafsilei because you're taking, you're holding onto it, so
it's like it's already collected. אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, אביי
Abaye said, אלא מעתה הלווהו ודר בחצרו ella me'ata hilvehu v'dar b'chatzeiro
דתפסי ליה d'tafsilei הכי נמי hachi nami ולא משמט? v'lo m'shamet? If
you lent him money and you just happen to be like living
in his property on his property, would we also say that it's
not משמט? m'shamet? Meaning, I get the- meaning, and presumably that means
if you take a look at תוספות, אין לפרש שדר בחצר של
הלווה שלא השכיר לו ein l'fareish she'dar b'chatzer shel halvei she'lo hiskir
lo מדהלא הלווהו ויש לו משכון mid'la hilvehu v'yeish lo mashkon בר
חבירו על חצירו ודר בחצירו. bar chaveiro al chatzeiro v'dar b'chatzeiro.
Okay, so let's say you actually lent him money and with the
right to collect
from- you'll seize his house if he hasn't paid up, and you
happen to be living in his house, you're renting his house. So
we should also say just cause it's physically in possession- now the
question is like, why not? Weren't we talking before about like קרקע
karka and שעבוד נכסים? shibud nechasim? But maybe again, maybe the גמרא
says that discussion was only when A, we were debating it, and
in the end רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan did not go that far,
did- said that it might not be enough that it's שעבוד נכסים
shibud nechasim even if it's written in the document. And maybe even
if it was good, it was only because it was explicitly written
in the document that really gave you real rights to it, real
partial ownership. But by this, it might be physically in your possession,
but where do we get the idea that you have that same
type of ownership in it, you know, that we were discussing before
by a case of קרקע karka when there was a שטר? shtar?
He's holding it, he's holding it. So the גמרא understands, first of
all you gotta remember also what does the תורה Torah say that
you do with a משכון? mashkon? You know what the תורה Torah
tells you you do with a משכון? mashkon? You give it back.
You give it back every night or every morning or whatever.
So A, so the point is, it might be that it's physically
in your possession, but as opposed to the discussions of קרקע karka
earlier, the גמרא assumes right now you don't have any real ownership
over it, so why should that be good enough? Let's see what
the answer is. It's a tricky- he quotes a פסוק. pasuk. So
anyway so the גמרא says like this, אמר ליה, amar lei, he
says back,
שאני משכון דקנה לדרבי יצחק. shani mashkon d'kaneh l'd'Rabbi Yitzchak. No, no,
no, a משכון mashkon maybe specifically מטלטלין metaltelin you actually do have
a part- a sense of an ownership over it based on the
דרשה drasha of רבי יצחק. Rebbi Yitzchak. דאמר רבי יצחק מנין לבעל
חוב שקונה משכון? d'amar Rabbi Yitzchak m'nayin l'ba'al chov she'koneh mashkon? How
do you know that the creditor owns the משכון mashkon to some
degree? שנאמר ולך תהיה צדקה. shene'emar u'lecha tihiyeh tzedakah. When you return
it that evening or the next morning, depending on whether it's a
night garment or a day garment, there will be righteousness will be
accorded to you. אם אינו קונה צדקה מנין? im eino koneh tzedakah
m'nayin? If you don't own it, why is it called צדקה? tzedakah?
Okay, 'cause it's meaning צדקה tzedakah as we define צדקה, tzedakah, not
the way the פסוק pasuk means by צדקה. tzedakah. צדקה tzedakah means
money of yours that you give to somebody else. Right. The righteous
thing to do. Right. So anyway מכאן לבעל חוב שקונה משכון. mikan
l'ba'al chov she'koneh mashkon. So you have some ownership over on it
and therefore, since it's like you already have taken possession of your
debt, שמיטה is not משמט. m'shamet. Okay. I unfortunately I think we're
just gonna have to end here. So I don't know, so we
will pick up tomorrow. Okay.